<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Buildings | OpenSensors.IO]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.opensensors.io/blog/categories/buildings/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.opensensors.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-12-13T19:08:23+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.opensensors.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[OpenSensors.IO]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Path to Smart Buildings]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.opensensors.io/blog/2016/10/05/path-to-smart-buildings-2/"/>
    <updated>2016-10-05T08:31:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.opensensors.io/blog/2016/10/05/path-to-smart-buildings-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Whether you are a building manager planning efficient space usage or an architect looking to design state-of-the-art buildings, we have broken down the steps to get you to your desired end goal. IoT planning should start with the business needs, of course, and quickly moves from the component layer all the way up to the application layer. We need to figure out what core data should be gathered and ways to effectively leverage that data. These IoT solutions require an end-to-end or device-to-cloud view.</p>

<p><img src="/images/OS Path to Smart-color.png" /></p>

<h2>A Phased implementation approach works best.</h2>

<p>We have found that the most successful IoT projects follow a phased implementation approach: Design Phase, Proof of Concept, Pilot, and Deployment. The design phase asks questions such as which sensors, who will be installing and maintaining the sensors. For Proof of Concept, a lab evaluation should include hooking up 5-8 sensors all the way through a gateway to data collection in the cloud. This will give enough real data to verify that the queries and the  analytics are feasible. The Pilot Phase ensures that the sensors work at scale and that the gateway configuration has been made easy for the deployment specialists. A pilot phase should be about 40 sensors depending on the density of the sensors. At this point, you can scale up to the number of sensors and the bandwidth required for full deployment.</p>

<h2>OpenSensors' Deployments</h2>

<p>We have built hardware, installation and network provider partnerships and relationships to help customers get rollouts live efficiently. Either roll out your own network or we will put you in touch with your local sensor installation specialist to take care of the install and maintenance.  We are working with customers and the community to understand what is required at each level for your IoT solution and can ease development and integration issues.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Savvy Building Managers Use Sensors to Reduce Operating Expenses]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.opensensors.io/blog/2016/09/08/savy-building-managers-use-sensors-to-reduce-operating-expenses/"/>
    <updated>2016-09-08T18:16:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.opensensors.io/blog/2016/09/08/savy-building-managers-use-sensors-to-reduce-operating-expenses</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Sensor networks are emerging as a mission critical method for offices and commercial spaces to save money. Offices and commercial spaces are undergoing a smart transformation by connecting and linking HVAC, lighting, environmental sensors, security, and safety equipment. Building and facilities managers are also installing utilization sensors to manage their spaces more efficiently.</p>

<p>Main benefits of data driven buildings
* Operational efficiency
* Use data for better design
* Better workspace experience for employees</p>

<h2>Changing workforce</h2>

<p>Recently we helped a company design a prototype of a desk sensor monitoring system. Because so many of their people were working from home they wanted to accurately measure the peak demand during the day to see if they could save 10-20% of their desk space. Goals for the system were:
* Monitor desk occupancy anonymously.
* Minimize installation and deployment costs: rely on solutions that were simple enough that existing non-expert personnel could be trained to deploy.
* Minimize day-to-day maintenance and deployment: this drove strategies for long battery life among others.
* Design a deployment process that ensured install team could easily add sensor location metadata to allow for rich reporting and analysis once IoT sensor network was operational.
* Limit the IT resources needed for deployment</p>

<h2>The  phased approach works best</h2>

<p>First, we looked at many sensors, evaluating quality, signal-to-noise ratio and power consumption. It&rsquo;s always a good idea to get a handful of different types of sensors and try them out in a very small scale. We chose an infrared red sensor with good battery life-time and a single LoRa gateway that could support all the floors and provide connection to the cloud.</p>

<p>Next we did a full end-to-end test, where we hooked up 5-10 sensors up completely to a cloud infrastructure all the way through the connectivity gateway. Now we had real data flowing into the infrastructure and could verify that the queries and analytics were feasible.  This step just makes sure everything works as planned and you will get all the data that you will need.</p>

<p>Once you&rsquo;re happy with the proof of concept phase, it is time for the real pilot phase. Instead of having just a handful of working sensors, now you&rsquo;ll hook up an entire floor or a street or whatever your use case might be. It should be somewhere between thirty, forty, maybe up to a hundred sensors. At this point you can ensure that the sensors work at scale and the gateway can handle the load. Typically we see customers running these for a month or two to get a good feel for how the sensors will perform in a production situation.</p>

<p>After the pilot phase, you should have enough data to verify network performance and your choices for sensors and gateways. Now you can plan the full deployment in detail. It’s been our experience, based on a number of customer installations, that the most successful IoT networks follow these steps in a phased implementation approach.</p>

<p> The technology at the silicon, software, and system level continues to evolve rapidly and our aim is to reduce the time to go live and minimise risk.  The internet of things is a nebulous term that includes quite a lot of specialised skillsets such as sensor manufacturing, network design, data analysis, etc.</p>

<p>In order to make projects successful, we have taken the approach of building many hardware, installation and network provider partnerships, and relationships to help customers succeed as opposed to trying to do it all ourselves.  We have been working with customers to develop methods to lower the sensor density and in turn lower the cost of projects whilst still getting comparable accuracy.</p>

<p>Contact us if you would like assistance on sensor selection, network design, or planning a proof of concept deployment.</p>

<p><img src="/images/office.jpg" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
