<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Cities | OpenSensors.IO]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.opensensors.io/blog/categories/cities/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.opensensors.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-10-07T11:08:09+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.opensensors.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[OpenSensors.IO]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[You Use Open Data Every Day]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.opensensors.io/blog/2015/05/17/you-use-open-data-every-day/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-17T13:11:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.opensensors.io/blog/2015/05/17/you-use-open-data-every-day</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You&rsquo;ve done your hair, you&rsquo;ve picked out the perfect outfit and you&rsquo;re set  on making a great first impression. How long have I got? What tube should I get? How soon is the next bus? You check the <a href="http://www.techworld.com/news/startups/londons-citymapper-capitalises-on-decade-of-data-3467301/">CityMapper app</a> &ndash; you find a route and within seconds know exactly how long it will take to get to your hot date. You may not know it, but open data has just made your trip a lot easier.</p>

<p>Transport for London, OpenStreetMaps, Foursquare, Google Maps, Apple Maps and Cyclestreets all provide access to <a href="http://theodi.org/what-is-open-data">open data</a> for others to use. In this case, CityMapper ingests the real-time open data produced by Transport for London, remixes it with freely available open mapping data, adds a touch of their own special sauce, real-time usage and congestion data from CityMapper users, and finally curates this brew in an accessible form for the user, waiting at the bus stop. In short, the CityMapper team takes the available open data, adds value to it and provides that as a service.</p>

<p>It is not an exaggeration to claim the future development of the city is <a href="http://theodi.org/research-afternoons/show-me-the-future-of-the-built-environment-and-open-data">intertwined</a> with open data. From transport data to air quality data to real time high-street footfall, as cities become leaner, genuinely smarter and more efficient the availability of reliable high quality data will become more important than ever. Generating open data from our surroundings is unlocking value and insight from our environment, information that is all around us, for the researcher, for the app developer, for the tinkerer, for the activist.</p>

<p>For cities to succeed in building resilient systems and networks, the emerging data ecosystem in the city can&rsquo;t rely on closed data, closed systems. Devices and sensors in the city won&rsquo;t function as JawBone and FitBit do, two closed devices whose real-time data I couldn&rsquo;t access and share even if I wanted to. Open data is disrupting the digital landscape, former data-as-commodity brokers, such as <a href="http://www.landmark.co.uk/">Landmark</a>, have since fundamentally reshaped the way in which they do business, focusing on curating available data.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Future Cities]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.opensensors.io/blog/2013/10/08/future-cities/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-08T13:07:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.opensensors.io/blog/2013/10/08/future-cities</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We were honored to be a platform partner and host the data for <a href="http://futurecitieshackathon.com/">The Future Cities Hackathon: Open Urban Data for The Citizens</a> a collaborative project by <a href="http://datasciencelondon.org/">Data Science London</a> during the weekend of the 5th &ndash; 6th of October.</p>

<p>Granular Data sets where provided by the City of Westminster by street and a period of around a year.
The full list data sets are below:</p>

<ul>
<li>Anti Social Behavior data</li>
<li>Dog fouling</li>
<li>Graffiti</li>
<li>Parking Sensors</li>
<li>Parking Tickets issued</li>
<li>Crowd Dynamics data measuring foot falls once an hour</li>
<li>Parking Cashless transactions data</li>
</ul>


<p>Participants spent the weekend working on projects aimed to improve the experiences of City of Westminster residents.  There were approximately 15 submissions in order to win one of 3 prizes.  The prize categories were for Statistical modelling, Data Visualisation and a Windows phone application.  The quality of the final submissions were outstanding.</p>

<p>A few of the submissions were</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Team &lsquo;Fjölmenni&rsquo;, who won the Statistical modeling challenge, made a &lsquo;CrowdWalk&rsquo; application that predicted how busy streets would be by time and day.</p></li>
<li><p>Team &lsquo;Kung fu pandas&rsquo; made a number of statistical models on parking spaces, one of the most interesting was finding under utilized car parking spaces.</p></li>
</ul>


<p><img src="/images/IMAG0731.jpg" /></p>

<ul>
<li>Team &lsquo;Street Sweep&rsquo; won the best Visualisation catergory and made a fantastic game 3d game using the opensensors.io api and open street map.  The game allowed players to clean dog fouling, vomit, etc from real data</li>
</ul>


<p><div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/jWkxDIYp6sU "></iframe></div></p>

<p>There were many more amazing projects submitted that could make the lives of people of Westminster so much easier.</p>

<h3>The Problem</h3>

<p>Unfortunately, getting the data in the first place was incredibly difficult.  The painful process and route that it took to get to us was described by Carlos in his talk.  The data was passsed between a multitude of intermediary companies and crossed the Oceans a few times in the below manner</p>

<p>&ldquo;Sensor device >  Data Provider > people > DB > people > ETL > people> CSV > public entity> people > ETL>  IT Vendor> DW > people > CSV > Sharepoint > Dropbox > and… us !!!&rdquo;</p>

<p>This process harms everyone from the council to residents. We can and need to simplify this process.</p>

<p>Smart environments need not be a dream of the distant future if we open the data and enable businesses and developers to build services for the benefit of everyone.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
