<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Institute | OpenSensors.IO]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.opensensors.io/blog/categories/institute/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.opensensors.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-17T12:30:59+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.opensensors.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[OpenSensors.IO]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[An Open Data Startup]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.opensensors.io/blog/2014/10/30/an-open-data-startup/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-30T18:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.opensensors.io/blog/2014/10/30/an-open-data-startup</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In that intense start up haze we occupy, the fact that
OpenSensors has turned 1 this month completely passed me
by! I feel that occasion should be marked with at least a post to
reflect on how far we have come in a year.</p>

<h2>An ODI startup <img src="/images/odi.png" /></h2>

<p>The highlight of the year has to be our inclusion to the
<a href="http://opendatainstitute.org/">Open Data Institute&rsquo;s</a> startup
program.</p>

<p>The ODI&rsquo;s mission is to unlock the potential of public data held by
governments and businesses to help solve the world&rsquo;s hard
problems. As our mission is to build a connected world based on open
data and technologies, being part of the ODI&rsquo;s network of like minded
people is the natural home for OpenSensors.</p>

<h2>Engineering Middleware is Hard</h2>

<p>The original middleware we designed and prototyped for OpenSensors has long been thrown
out, actually rewritten several times. We have spent hundreds of
engineering hours making it fast and secure. We can now comfortably process millions of
messages per second from hundreds of thousands of devices.  And most
importantly we let each of our users get their own real time feeds of data that they are interested in.</p>

<p>If you told me a year ago that it would take this long to build the
middleware we would be happy with, how I would have laughed at you&hellip;.</p>

<h2>Hardware is very Hard</h2>

<p>After spending some time working under the radar, towards the middle of 2014 the Internet
of Things
<a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/gilpress/2014/08/18/its-official-the-internet-of-things-takes-over-big-data-as-the-most-hyped-technology/">hypecycle</a>
suddenly went into overdrive.</p>

<p>That being said designing and manufacturing hardware products at scale
is a significantly different proposition to scaling software. The
skill sets necessary to build and manufacture electronics products is
rare and laborious. We have found ourselves in the surprising position
of prototyping hardware for clients and cities as well as learning the
process of manufacturing.</p>

<h2>Aims for the coming year</h2>

<p>Our central ambition for the next year is to make it very easy for
people to find and contribute to rich sources of real time data that is of interest to them.</p>

<p>We have some exciting partnerships and projects with various cities and
groups in parking, disability accessibility and smart buildings all publishing open data. We
also want to help showcase the excellent work of the many community
based environmental sensing projects.</p>

<h2>Sunsetting the early access period</h2>

<p>As of the 1st of December 2014, we will be charging for private use of the
service. Open Data projects will always be free. Private projects
will incur a small monthly cost towards the service based on the
number of devices you run.</p>

<p>For a full details of the pricing, see <a href="https://opensensors.io/pricing">https://opensensors.io/pricing</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
